It's you.
是你
The phantom piper!
幽灵风笛手！
No!
不！
No! I'll not go with you!
不！我不跟你走！
Do you hear me, piper? No! Leave me!
你听到了没, 风笛手？不, 走开！
Leave me. I'll not go with you, do you hear me?
走开．我不跟你走, 你听到了没？
Leave me! No, I'll not go with you!
走开！不, 我不跟你走！
I'll fight you every inch of the way.
我每一步都要跟你斗
I'll not go with you.
我不跟你走
Leave me, piper.
走开, 风笛手
No. Leave me. I'll not go.
不, 走开, 我不走
Agh!
啊
- Polly, what's happened?
- Oh, Doctor, it was horrible!
- Polly, 发生什么事了？  - 哦, 博士, 太吓人了
- A giant creature like a Cyberman!
- It's all right. Don't be frightened.
- 一个赛博人一样的大家伙  - 没事了, 别怕
- Whatever it was, it's gone now.
- It's the... Doctor, the Cyberman was carrying a patient.
- 不管是什么, 现在已经走了 - 那是...博士, 那个赛博人扛着一个病人
- Cyberman? What are you talking about?
- I'm sure it was.
- 赛博人？你在说些什么？  - 我确定是
- I'll not go with you.
- It's OK. It's safe now. Take it easy.
- 我不跟你走  - 没事了, 现在安全了, 放松
She's right. There's another one gone.
她是对的, 又有一个不见了
Sam, Jules, you've got to find these men.
They can't just disappear in a place this size.
Sam, Jules, 你们去找这几个人．他们不可能消失了, 就这么点大个地方
Search every square inch, don't come back
until you find them. Now move.
每一寸都要搜到, 找不到他们就不要回来．快去
Now, supposing you tell me your story? What did you see?
现在, 来跟我说说你的故事？你看到了什么？
I went out to get Jamie some water,
我出去给 Jamie 倒点水
and when I came back,
I saw this giant man or creature or something,
当我回来的时候, 我看到一个高大的人或者生物什么的
just going out of the door,
carrying one of the patients... like a doll.
它正走出门去, 扛着一个我们的病人...像个玩偶一样
- I think it was a Cyberman.
- Forget that part. Then what?
- 我觉得那是个赛博人  - 忘了那个吧．然后呢？
Then nothing. The door shut, and then you came in.
然后没什么了．门关上了, 然后你们进来了
- What do you know about all this?
- Nothing. Absolutely nothing.
- 这一切你都知道些什么？  - 没什么, 什么也不知道
We'll see about that in a minute.
我们稍后再来讨论
- This thing you saw. What was it like?
- It was enormous, and silver.
- 你看见的这个东西, 它是什么样子？  - 很高大, 银色外形
- It had holes in its head for eyes, like a robot.
- A robot?
- 脑袋上眼睛那个位置有洞, 像个机器人一样  - 像个机器人?
But the Cybermen were all killed when Mondas blew up.
但 Mondas 爆炸的时候赛博人都死了啊
Stop this Cyberman nonsense!
别胡说赛博人那些东西了
There were Cybermen, every child knows that,
but they were destroyed ages ago!
以前是有赛博人, 每个小孩子都知道．但他们几十年前就被消灭了！
（注:  赛博人初次出现于1986年, 试图夺取地球, 后与母星 Mondas 一起毁灭
参见04x01 第十行星 The Tenth Planet）
- So we all thought.
- That's enough.
- 我们都这么想  - 别再说了
Let's have a little calm thinking.
我们都冷静地想一想
For the past two weeks,
a complete unknown disease has appeared in the base.
过去两个星期以来, 一种完全未知的疾病出现在这个基地
People drop in their tracks
and develop a black pattern on their skin.
人在工作岗位上倒下, 皮肤上长出黑色的条纹
Then some of the patients disappear, right?
然后又有一些病人消失了, 对不？
They can't leave the base without wearing spacesuits,
and there are no spacesuits missing. So where are they?
不穿太空服的花他们不可能离开基地, 但又没有太空服丢失．那他们在哪儿？
- I must say, It does sound a little odd.
- More than a little.
- 我得说, 这事听着是有一点点奇怪  - 不是一点点
I do know one thing - a new disease starts,
people disappear, and then you turn up.
我倒的确知道一件事情 - 新疾病出现, 人们消失, 然后你们出现了
- And you think we did it!
- Oh, come on, we haven't done a thing!
- 那你就觉得是我们干的？  - 哦, 得了, 我们什么也没干！
Perhaps maybe, I don't know who you are,
what you are, or where you came from,
也许吧, 我也不知道你们是谁, 是干什么的, 从哪里来
but you can get off the moon now!
但你们现在就可以离开月球了！
- Well, that suits me fine, the sooner the better!
- No, Ben, we can't go yet.
- 好啊, 正想走呢, 越早越好！  - 不, Ben, 我们还不能走
- Why not? They don't want us here.
- Because there is something evil here. We must stay.
- 为什么不？他们不想让我们在这里 - 因为这里有邪恶的东西, 我们必须留下来
- Evil? Don't be daft!
- Evil is what I meant.
- 邪恶？ 别犯傻了！   - 邪恶．我说的就是这个
There are some corners of the universe
which have bred the most terrible things.
宇宙中有些角落会孕育出最可怕的东西
Things which act against everything
that we believe in. They must be fought.
这些东西会跟我们所信仰的一切作对．我们必须跟他们斗争
This disease, for instance. It isn't really
a disease at all, but I can help you with it.
举例来说, 这个疾病, 其实并不是一种病．但我可以帮助你们
You'll see. I'll find the cause for you.
你会看到, 我会帮你们找到原因
- Will you, indeed?
- Yes, certainly. I just need to examine a few things. That's all.
- 会吗, 真的？ - 当然．我需要先检验几样东西, 仅此而已
- It should be simple.
- Well, I'm not sure.
- 那很简单  - 嗯, 我不太确定
I'll give you just one Earth-day cycle to find the cause.
我给你一个地球日的时间来寻找原因
- Earth what?
- 24 hours.
- 地球什么？  - ２４小时
- But that's no time at all.
- It's all you're going to get.
- 但这时间也太短了吧  - 你们只有这些时间
Then you get off the moon, with this bloke here.
然后你们就离开月球, 带着这个家伙
- You can't move him! He's very ill.
- We accept.
- 你不能乱动他, 他病得很厉害  - 我们接受
Now tell me, you have pathological equipment here, yes?
现在说说, 你们这里有病理分析设备吧？
Yes. Evans was working on an extensive research project.
It's all in here.
有．Evans 之前在做一个扩展研究项目．东西都在这里
It's quite a small unit. We're not equipped
to deal with a full-scale epidemic.
是一套小型设备, 我们并没有针对大规模传染病的配置
- Do you think you can manage?
- Yes. I think I can.
- 你觉得你能搞定吗？ - 是的，我觉得我能
Right. I'll leave you to it. Don't forget - 24 hours.
好, 我就不打扰你了．不要忘了 - ２４小时
- What are you going to do, Doctor?
- We'll start with this one.
- 你打算怎么做, 博士？ - 我们从这个开始
- Are you really a medical doctor?
- Yes, I think I was once
- 你真是一个医学博士吗？  - 是的, 我想我曾经做过
Polly, I think I took a degree once, in Glasgow.
Polly, 我记得我拿到了学位, 在格拉斯哥
1888, I think. Lister. Hold that for me, will you?
1888年, 没记错的话. 李斯特．帮我把住这里, 行吗
（约瑟夫-李斯特 英国外科医生, 外科手术消毒技术的发明者和推广者）
- Oh!
- All right. He's quite unconscious.
- 噢！  - 没事, 他完全没意识了
It's all right, Jamie. It's all right.
You're going to get better but you must lie still.
没事的, Jamie, 没事．你会好起来的, 但你必须要躺好
What is this place? Is it the home of the piper?
这是什么地方？这是风笛手的家吗？
No, we're on the moon. You know, the moon up in the sky.
不, 我们在月球上．你知道吗, 天上的月亮
No, I can't be alive.
不, 我不可能还活着
I've just seen the piper.
我刚才看见了风笛手
The piper! I knew!
风笛手！我就知道！
Polly! What's happened?
Polly! 发生了什么事？
Polly.
Are you all right?
你没事吧？
Nothing. Absolutely nothing.
没有，什么都没有
- Isn't there any clue at all?
- No. It's a complete blank.
- 一点线索也没有吗？  - 没有, 完全的空白
All the tests are negative. As far as I can see,
this whole ridiculous place is sterile.
所有测试结果都是阴性的．就我所看到的来说, 这整个破地方都是无菌的
We'll have to tell Mr Hobson, I suppose.
- 我们不得不跟 Hobson 先生说了, 我想
I don't like it very much. I simply don't understand it.
我不喜欢这个结果。我就是想不明白
Doctor, it couldn't possibly have
anything to do with Lister, could it?
博士, 这会不会跟李斯特有关, 可能吗？
- Lister?
- Well, I mean, you did say
- 李斯特  - 这样, 我是说, 你不是说
that you took your degree in Glasgow in 1888.
你1888年在格拉斯哥拿到了学位
That's an awfully long time from now, 2070, whatever it is.
那可是一段好长的时间了, 现在是2070年了
Polly, are you suggesting that I'm not confident to carry out these tests?
Polly, 你是不是想说我并没有能力进行这些检测？
No, No, I'm just wondering if there was anything
that Joseph Lister didn't know in 1888
不, 不, 我只是在想会不会有些什么东西是约瑟夫-李斯特在1888年不知道的
- that might help you now.
- Ssh! Somebody's coming!
- 说不定可以帮上你  - 嘘, 有人来了！
It's Mr Hobson. Out for blood - ours. Look busy! Quick!
是 Hobson 先生． 去拿血样 - 我们的．装作忙碌, 快！
That's the third person to disappear in the past few hours.
这是在过去几个小时内消失的第三个人了
- It's completely illogical.
- Do you mind?
- 这完全没逻辑  - 可以吗？
Would you mind standing away from the door
and allowing it to close? The slides. The dust!
你别站在门边可以吗, 让门可以关上？检测片. 灰尘！
It must be you people.
We've got some straight talking to do, you and I.
肯定是你的人．我们得好好谈一谈了, 你跟我
- Polly. Another boot.
- Do you hear me?
- Polly, 再来一下  - 你听到我的话了吗？
- This is extraordinary. Look here.
- Excuse me, please.
- 这真是不寻常啊, 看这里  - 借过一下, 请
Excuse me. We ARE trying to help you.
对不起, 我们正在试图帮你忙呢
- Help? Is that what you call it? You can all get off the moon now.
- No, wait a minute. You said...
- 帮忙？你管这个叫帮忙？你们现在就可以离开月球了 - 不, 等一下, 你说过...
- I don't care what I said!
- Ah!
- 我不管我说过什么！  - 哈！
- Have you found something?
- I think perhaps I have.
- 你发现什么了吗？  - 我想也许我发现了
Yes, I may be onto something, but I must have some room.
是的, 我可能找到点头绪, 但我必须得有空间
How can I work under these conditions? Now, please,
come along. Outside. I'm trying to work in here!
在这种条件下我怎么工作？ 现在, 请过来, 外面去．我在这里尽力工作呢
- Ben, see that they stay outside.
- Did you mean that?
- Ben, 确保他们待在外面  - 你真的吗？
- What?
- You've found something?
- 什么？  - 你发现了点什么？
Oh, Polly, I only wish I had.
哦, Polly, 我也期望我是
- Coffee? Sugar?
- Hello, Doctor. Thank you.
- 要咖啡不？ 糖？  - 你好, 博士．谢谢你
- It's very hot. Doctor, what about you?
- Thank you, Polly.
- 这很热. 博士, 你要吗？ - 谢谢你, Polly
Doctor, as I was saying, you've had your chance.
You come up with absolutely nothing.
博士, 如我之前说过的, 给过你们机会了．但你的结果是完全的空白
Don't touch him!
别碰他！
Let me look.
我看看
Charlie and you, Ben, give us a hand
to get him into the medical unit.
Charlie 和你 Ben, 搭一下手, 把他弄到医务室去
Try not to touch his skin.
尽量不要碰到他的皮肤
Don't drink that! It's the sugar!
不要喝那个！是糖！
Don't you see? That's why the disease doesn't affect everyone.
你明白了吗？那就是为什么这个病没有感染每一个人
It's the sugar. Not everyone takes it.
是糖有问题, 不是每个人都加糖
Don't touch it.
别碰它
- What are you doing?
- Just be patient.
- 你在干什么  - 耐心点
Just as I thought.
正如我所料想的
A large neurotropic virus.
一种大型的神经病毒
- Like the space plague?
- No.
- 就像太空瘟疫? - 不
（注: 太空瘟疫是科幻小说 Highways in Hiding 所描绘的一种疾病,
初始表象是手指脚趾硬化, 然后扩散到四肢以及全身. 此小说的简略版名称即为"太空瘟疫")
It's a large infective agent that only attacks the nerves.
这是一种大型感染剂, 只攻击神经系统
That's why these patients got these lines appear on faces and hands.
这就是为什么那些病人脸上手上会出现那些条纹
It follows the course of the nerves under the skin.
它沿着皮下的神经脉络走动
That's _ it well. But how did it get in here?
但它怎么进入这个地方的？
It is the Cybermen. I believe they have
deliberately infected the base.
是赛博人．我相信是他们故意传染了这个基地
My men have searched every square of the base.
我的人搜索了这个基地的每一寸地方
There's no space to hide a cat, let alone a Cyberman.
这个地方连只猫都没地方躲, 更别说赛博人了
Anyhow, how did they get in?
不管怎么说, 他们怎么进来的
- One moment.
- What is it?
- 等一下  - 什么
- You say you searched all the base?
- Yes. What of it?
- 你说你们把整个基地搜遍了？ - 是啊, 怎么？
- No chance of anyone hiding anywhere?
- None whatever.
- 任何人没有机会躲在什么地方？  - 没有任何机会
Did your men search in here? Did they?
你的人搜过这里吗？搜过没？
- There was'nt people in here, so...
- Did they search in here?
- 之前这里没有人, 所以... - 他们搜过这里没有？
- No.
- There's nowhere in here they could hide.
- 没有  - 这里没有可以躲藏的地方
Oh, no! Back!
噢, 不！后退！
Back.
后退